Guide to the Records of the Student Army Training Corps RG.43.1
New York University Archives
Records of the Student Army Training Corps
1916-1969
New York University Archives
Brown, Marshall Stewart, 1870-1948
RG.43.1
2.25 Linear Feet (6 boxes)
The records of the Student Army Training Corps Program (SATC) unit are part of the papers of Dean Marshall S. Brown, who served as chairman of New York University's (NYU's) SATC Committee from September 1918 to Spring 1919. The material includes both internal and external correspondence and memoranda, mainly between the members of NYU's SATC Committee and officials in various government departments.
Separated Material
Several items, including a photograph entitled "Presenting the Flag", have been removed from the collection.
Related Material at the New York University Archives
Charles H. Snow Collection on NYU During World War I, MC 25; William Bryans Papers, MC 29
Scope and Contents
The records of the Student Army Training Corps unit at NYU are part of the papers of Dean Marshall S. Brown, who served as chairman of NYU's SATC Committee from September 1918 to the following spring. The material includes both internal and external correspondence and memoranda, mainly between the members of NYU's SATC Committee and officials in various government departments. Also included are War Department circulars, reports on the condition of the detachment and progress of work, general and special military orders, SATC course handbooks, rosters, and lists of personnel. The bulk of the material falls in the period between March 1918 and December 1918, the period in which the National Army Training Detachment and, later, the SATC were active. However, exploratory material began as early as February 1917, and material relating to the settlement of contracts with the War Department, dismantling of facilities and evaluation of the program extends to June 1919. In addition, there is material relating to the establishment of the Reserve Officer Training Corps (ROTC), which covers the period from May 1918 to 1969.
World War I and the Student Army Training Corps are benchmarks in the history of cooperation between the military and educational institutions. The NYU SATC records include material that sheds light on that relationship, including contracts between NYU and the government; material on the development of curricula, most significantly the "War Issues" course; and memoranda offering suggestions for the final report submitted "for the historical record" to the War Department, as well as a copy of the complete report. Announcements, statements of policy, and committee minutes also provide information on the University's participation in the war effort.
Much of the material relates to the day-to-day functioning of the organization. There are highly detailed accounts of the numerical strength of the unit, including daily reports of "changes" in officers and enlisted personnel, muster rolls, and bi-weekly reports of unit strength. These and other rosters and lists of students and applicants shed light on the make-up of the student body and those participating in the program. Letters of application, and applications for discharge often include information on the individual's family and financial status, and provide further indication of the student body and its attitude toward the program.
The large amount of circulars, memoranda, and announcements from the War Department Committee on Education and Special Training, and its district offices, as well as the special organizational chart outlining the activities of the National Army Training Detachment and the SATC, provide information on how the NYU unit fit into the national SATC effort.
History of the Student Army Training Corps at New York University
The Student Army Training Corps (SATC) at New York University was part of a nationwide program initiated by the Committee on Education and Special Training of the War Department during World War I. Begun in the spring of 1918 as the National Army Training Detachments, it was demobilized the following December after the Armistice.
In April 1918 the National Army Training Detachments program was established at 157 colleges, universities, and trade schools under contract with the War Department. The program was designed to train draftees in a variety of trades needed for the war effort, and was jointly administered by the military and the schools. The proposed Student Army Training Corps, according to one historian, would serve to develop "as a great military asset the large body of young men in the colleges and ... [to prevent] unnecessary and wasteful depletion of the colleges through indiscriminate volunteering, by offering the student a definite and immediate military status." (Gruber, Mars and Minerva, p. 215)
Even before the training detachments got underway, the Army realized it lacked the required officers. At the same time, colleges were concerned about the depletion of students by the war and the attendant financial loss, which was only partially redressed by the vocational program. NYU in particular had been financially dependent to a large degree on tuition, much of which was lost by student enlistment.
At NYU Captain (later Major) William S. Maulsby was the military program commander, and Charles Snow, dean of the College of Engineering, was the civilian director of the National Army Training Detachment. Fifteen committees, made up of faculty and staff of the University, were appointed to administer specific areas. The school agreed to provide the soldiers with instruction, food, and quarters. The government, in turn, agreed to reimburse the University a fixed amount per soldier.
The first group of soldiers arrived on April 11 and, together with later inductees, received instruction geared toward becoming auto mechanics, blacksmiths, carpenters, chauffeurs, concrete workers, electricians, machinists, and radio operators. During a two-month period, the men received training in their trades, military instruction and, beginning in July, a course on "War Issues."
At the beginning of the fall semester, 524 institutions enrolled about 140,000 men into SATC units. At that time, the National Army Training Detachments were absorbed into SATC as Section B vocationals. In all, between April 11 and demobilization on December 19, 1918, 1,613 men took part in this section at NYU.
NYU agreed to accept 2,000 men. The NYU SATC unit eventually enrolled 1,564 student-soldiers in two divisions: 1,288 at University Heights and 276 at University and Bellevue Hospital Medical College. Marshall S. Brown, dean of Faculties, was appointed chairman of the SATC Committee and Archibald L. Bouton, dean of the College of Arts and Pure Science, became head of Section A (academics), while Dean Snow continued as head of Section B (vocationals), and Captain Maulsby remained as military commander.
Unlike the "Fighting Mechanics" of the Training Detachments, the collegiate or Section A SATC students were required to fulfill the requirements for college admission and to be accepted as matriculated students by the schools they attended. Inducted as privates in the regular army and subject to military discipline, the student-soldiers lived in barracks, ate at mess and were accorded a monthly allowance of $30 in addition to having their tuition paid. They were to receive a total of 42 hours of "essential" and "allied" subjects while also performing military drill for 11 hours per week. Essential courses included "military law and practice," "hygiene and sanitation," "surveying and map making," "modern ordinance," and the "war issues" course. At the end of their studies (between one and three terms, depending on age), the students were assigned to officer or non-commissioned officer training programs, a depot brigade, or permitted further study in engineering, medicine, or law.
The Armistice interrupted the work of the SATC shortly after it began. After some debate over whether or not it should be continued, the SATC was demobilized on December 19, 1918. Within six months, the work of demobilization and fulfilling contracts between the government and the schools was completed.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The SATC program records were presumably transferred to Gould Memorial Library on the University Heights campus of NYU from the Dean of Faculties, Marshall S. Brown. They remained in storage until 1974, when they were transferred to Washington Square following the closing of the Heights campus.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged chronologically in three series:
Series I: Interdepartmental Correspondence and Memoranda; Series II: Administrative Files; Series III: Reports and Memoranda
Conditions Governing Access
Material pertaining to individual student records may be restricted in accordance with the Family Educational Rights and Privacy Act (FERPA). Please contact the Archives with specific questions regarding access to such records.
Sources
Brown, Marshall S. "Report to the War Department of the Chairman of the Committee on the Students' Army Training Corps," in New York University. Report of Officers, 1918-1919 (New York, 1919) pp. 69-85.
Gruber, Carol S. Mars and Minerva: World War I and the Uses of Higher Learning in America. (Baton Rouge, 1975).
Report of the Chancellor. "Military Training" in New York University. Report of Officers, 1918-1919 (New York, 1919) pp.14-15.
Report of the Treasurer in New York University, Report of Officers, 1918-1919 (New York, 1919) pp. 29-31.
Snow, Charles Henry. The Camp on Campus: The Great War as Observed from a College. Unpublished Manuscript, NYU Archives.
Organizational charts.; Curricula.; World War, 1914-1918; Military discharges.; Military education -- United States -- History -- 20th century; Orders (military records).; Muster rolls.; Minutes (administrative records); Contracts; United States. War Department. Committee on Education and Special Training; New York University. College of Medicine; United States. Army. Students' Army Training Corps; Bouton, Archibald Lewis, 1872-1941; Brown, Elmer Ellsworth, 1861-1934; Maulsby, William S.; New York University -- Students; New York University. National Army Training Detachment; New York University. Reserve Officer Training Corps; Snow, Charles H. (Charles Henry), 1863-1957; New York University. School of Applied Science; New York University. Student Army Training Corps; New York University. Washington Square College of Arts and Science
- Series I: Interdepartmental Correspondence and Memoranda, 1916-1919
  Scope and Contents note
  Series includes internal and external communication between the members of the New York University Student Army Training Committee (SATC) and officers of various governmental departments.
  - Snow, Charles H., 1916 Jan - 1919 May (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Treasury Department, 1916 Dec - 1919 Jan (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Brown, Elmer E., 1917 - 1919 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Adjutant General, 1918 - 1919 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Brown, Elmer E., 1918-1919 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - District #2, 1918-1919 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - CEST, General Staff Corps, 1918-1919 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Eastern Department, 1918-1919 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - War Department, Office of the Chief Signal Officer, 1918 Jan (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Brown, Marshall S. [SATC Committee Chairman], 1918 Feb-1918 Dec (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - University Heights, 1918 Apr-1918 Oct (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - U. S. Army Hospital #1, 1918 May-1918 Aug (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Administrative Officer, 1918 May-1918 September (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - American Council on Education: Student War Service Campaign, 1918 Aug-1918 Dec (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - CEST, Provost Marshal General's Department, 1918 Sep-1918 Oct (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Director of College Training, 1918 Sep-1919 Jul (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Bouton, Archibald, 1918 Sep-1918 Dec (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Park, Dr. W. H., 1918 Sep-1918 Dec (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Maulsby, Commander W. S., 1918 Sep-1918 Nov (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Brown, Marshall S., 1918 Sep-1918 Oct (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Administrative Officer, 1918 Oct (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Administrative Officer, 1918 Nov-1918 Dec (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Office of Surgeon General, 1918 Nov-1918 Dec (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - General Correspondence, 1918 Nov (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - University Heights, 1918 Nov-1919 Apr (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - General Correspondence, 1918 Dec-1919 Jun (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - War Department, Zone Finance Office, 1919 Mar (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Series II: Administrative Files, 1917-1969
  Series includes War Department bulletins, circulars, contracts, discharge orders, general, and special orders. There are also university records such as minutes, organizational charts, maps, physical descriptions of barracks, information on the courses taught, insight into the liquidation of SATC, and the formation of an ROTC program.
  - Office of Surgeon General, 1918 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - SATC Admissions letters of inquiry, 1918 Sep-1918 Nov (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Blank SATC Forms, undated (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - SATC Headquarters Eastern Department Bulletin, 1918 Nov (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - SATC Headquarters at University Heights Bulletin, 1918 Sept (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Committee on Education and Special Training Bulletin, 1918 Nov-1919 March (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Charge Sheets: NYU SATC Unit, 1918 Jul-1918 Dec- (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Certificate, War Dept., Signal Corps - Office of Aviation Examining Board, Physical Examination, 1918 Nov (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Christmas Committee of New York University: SATC Christmas Card, 1918 Dec (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Circulars: SATC Headquarters, District #2, 1918 Nov-1918 Dec (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Circulars: War Department, General, 1918 - 1919 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Circulars: War Department, Special Descriptive, undated (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Contracts: War Department, CEST, 1918 Mar-1918 Jun (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Contracts: War Department, Office of Surgeon General, 1918 - 1919 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Discharge Orders: SATC Headquarters, Eastern Department, 1918 Dec-1919 Feb (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Discharge Orders: SATC Headquarters, University Heights, 1918 Jun-1919 Jan (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - History of SATC at NYU Draft, undated (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Minutes: Executive Committee of the War Council [War Emergency Conference], 1918 Feb-1918 Jun (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Minutes: University Committee of SATC, 1918 Sep (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Naval Section of SATC, 1917-1919 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - War Department General Orders, 1918 Sep-1918 Oct (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Special orders SATC Headquarters Camp Devens, MA, 1918 May-1918 Jun (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Special orders SATC Headquarters Camp Plattsburg, NY, 1918 May-1918 Oct (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Special orders Eastern Department, 1918-1919 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Special orders University Heights, 1918-1919 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Special orders various camps, 1918 Apr-1918 Oct (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Spcial orders War Department, Adjutant General, 1918 May-1918 Nov (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Organization Chart of SATC at NYU, undated (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - ROTC Information, 1918-1921 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Selective Service Act Rules and Regulations, 1918 Sep (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Settlement and Liquidation OF SATC, 1919 Jan-1919 May (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Description and Maps of SATC Buildings at NYU, undated (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - SATC Courses: Human Side of Engineering, undated (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - SATC Courses: Machinists, undated (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - SATC Courses: War Issues, information, 1918 Jun-1918 Dec (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - ROTC at NYU, 1923-1969 (Box 6)
- Series III: Reports and Memoranda, 1918-1919
  Arranged in chronological order. Series includes internal and external communication between the members of the NYU Student Army Training Corpos and officers of various governmental departments.
  - Faculty Teaching SATC courses, undated (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - SATC Student Enrollment, 1918-1919 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Report of Changes: List of Officers, 1918-1919 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Roster of NYU Training Detachment, 1918-1919 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Statement of Claim for Reimbursement of Costs, 1918 Mar-1918 Sep (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Payroll Reports: General, 1918 Apr-1918 Jul (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Condition of the Organization Report, 1918 Apr-1918 Dec (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Muster Roll, 1918 Apr-1918 Jun (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - School Rating Reports, 1918 May-1918 Oct (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Draft Discharge List, 1918 Jul-1918 Aug (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Report of Changes: Enlisted Men, 1918 Jul-1918 Sep (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Payroll Reports, 1918 Aug-1918 Oct (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Medical Enlisted Reserve Corps members, 1918 Oct (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Men Inducted into SATC, 1918 Oct (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Men Recommended for SATC, 1918 Oct-1918 Nov (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Men rejected as physically unfit for service, 1918 Oct (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Students accepted for SATC admission, 1918 Oct (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Report of Changes: Enlisted Men, 1918 Oct (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Engineering Students, 1918 Nov (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Bi-weekly Report to CEST, 1918 Nov (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Men Receiving Physical Exams, 1918 Nov-1918 Dec (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Payroll Reports, 1918 Nov-1918 Dec (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Semimonthly Report to CEST, 1918 Nov-1918 Dec (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Final Report, Special Detachments, 1918 Dec (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Final Report, Companies A - I, 1918 Dec (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - Report for Historical Record: SATC at NYU, 1919 Jan (Box 5, Folder 4)